American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIa. 1743-1806 APS.Archives.IIa APS.Archives.IIa
American Philosophical Society
American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIa
1743-1806
APS.Archives.IIa
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the American Philosophical Society Archives. For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
American Philosophical Society.
- Papers
  - BRACKETED DATES
    - Letter to John Vaughan, [1789]; 9x7-1/2; Vaughan, Samuel, 1720-1802
      Scope and Contents note
      A.L.S. 2p. Presents West Indian objects to the APS through his brother, J.Vaughan. On same sheet as letter from J.Vaughan to B.Franklin; Dec.18,1789. Film 54-57 Frame 78
    - Letter to Dr. Franklin, Pres. of A.P.S., May 14, [1789]; 7 1/2" x 9"; Aitken, Robert, 1735-1802
      A.L.S. 1p. Financial complications; possibility of suit being instituted against him. FILM 54-57 FRAME 76
    - Letter to J. P. Lesley, Dec. 26, [18]74; 10x8; Rantoul literary society
      Rantoul, Ill., A.L.S.: A. H. Bailey, president. 1p., seal. Apprises A.P.S. of progress made by his society.
    - Particular account of the Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London bound, [1801]; 13x8; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      A.D. 3p.and end. List of Transactions in possession of the APS. Notes certain volumes bond "not of D[r.] Franklins."
    - Settlement of accounts left unpaid by Samuel Vaughan, [1802]; 5x8; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
      A.D.S.with initials. 1p.
    - Letter to W. Roxburgh, [1803]; 8x5; Moore, Richard Channing, 1762-1841
      Sunday. L.S. 1p.and add. Concerning a skeleton.
    - Bill of mortality, [1803]; Portsmouth (N.H.)
      Broadside. 1p. O. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 22a.) Cf. Minutes, p.334. Enclosed originally in letter from Spalding to J.R. Coxe; Feb. 21, 1803. Pres. by Lyman Spalding; (reed.)4 March 1803.
    - J[oseph] Priestley to the members of the American Philosophical Society, March 2, [1803]; 7 15/16" x 9 3/4"; Priestley, Joseph
      [Philadelphia], 1 p. A.L.S. Accepts invitation to dine with the members of the Society. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 334.
  - Letter to Tho[mas] Jefferson, Washington, Dec. 28, 1804; 11x8; Demaree, Samuel R.
    Harrodsburg, A.L.S. 3p. and add., end. (see Ms. Comm. to APS. Phil.,Lit.,Ant.,Geo. Education. vol. 1, no.17.) Concerning Writing and spelling.
  - NOT FOUND
    - Extract from the history of the Royal Society of London, February 22, 1681/2; 8 1/4" x 13 1/8"
      Read before A.P.S., 2pp. and endorsement. D.S.: Wm. Jones; endorsed, Jn. Vaughan. Copy. From original copy read by B. Franklin. Notation by John Vaughan that treasurer should bring suit against members who refuse payment of their arrears.
    - Concerning telegraphy, May 21, 1684; 12x7; Hooke, Robert, 1635-1703
      [received from William Dunbar]; Jan.16, D. 7p.and end. Copy. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 22.) Delivered originally before the Royal Society of London. Printed: Hooke's Phil. (Hobson's Extracts) p.142.
    - Letter to Rev. St. George, (bishop of Clagher), July 29, 1715; 9x7; Nevil, Francis
      Belturbet, L. Copy. 4p. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 4.) Concerning a fossil bone.
    - Letter to the Archbishop of Ireland, 1715?; 9x7; Molyneux, Thomas, Sir, 1661-1733
      [ca.]. L. Extract. 12p.and drawing of 1p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 54.) Concerning mammoth fossil teeth. Enclosed originally in letter from Bogert to J.Vaughan; Dec. 20, 1817.
    - Meteorological observations, Aug. 1748-Sept. 1749
    - Concerning the parhelia rainbows and halo which appeared in Philadelphia, Dec. 21, 1756; 13x8; Williamson, Hugh, 1735-1819
      [presented by George Logan] May 20, 1816. D.S. 1p.and end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 52.) For the account of this phenomenon, see: Account of two parhelia; Dec. 21, 1756.
    - Caradoc, Sir John Francis, 1762-1839; Cradock, Fred
      see
    - Proposals for enlarging this Society in order that it may the better answer the End for which it was instituted, namely, the promoting and propagating useful knowledge, Jan. 1, 1768; 13x8-1/2; Thomson, Charles, 1729-1824
      D. 10p. (see Minutes of the Junto and American society for promoting useful knowledge (in middle of volume), pp.61-70.) Printed (with slightly different wording) APS. Transactions, vol.I,o.s Preface
    - Catalogue of donations to the A.P.S., 1768-1897; [1898?]; 12x8; American Philosophical Society. Curators
      D. 58p. Compiled by Mr. Hunersdorff. Cf. A.P.S. Curators' Annual report for 1901. Pages 15, 38 missing.
    - Letter to [the American philosophical society?], Jan. 10, 1769; 13x8; Jacobs, Benjamin
      Philadelphia County, L. Copy. 4p. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 2.) Concerning Carter's article on the fly weevil and a cure for it.
    - Frederic Guyer to the [American] Philosophical society, 1769; 7 15/16" x 9 3/8"; Guyer, Frederic
      ----, 3 pp., address and endorsement. A.Com.S. Method of ascertaining the longitude by lunar observation, submitted for Magellanic premium. Read, January 15, 1796 See Pro., xxII, pt. 3, 236.
    - Letter to Dr. Benjamin Franklin, Craven Street, Dec. 11, 1769; 9x7; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
      Greenwich, A.L. in 3d.P. 3p. and add., end. Mutilated. (see Ms.Comm.to APS. Math and Astronomy, vol. 1, no. 6.) Concerning the transit of Venus of 1769. Printed: APS Trans.,v.1,ed.1,p.90.
    - Letter to Benj[amin] Franklin, Craven Street, Dec. 27, 1769; 8x6-1/2; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
      Greenwich, A.L.S. 2p. and add., end. (see Ms.Comm.to APS. Math and Astronomy, vol. 1, no.7.) Transit of Venus of 1769 and concerning the Philadelphia group.
    - Letter to [William] Smith, Dec. 26, 1769; 12x7-1/2; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
      Greenwich, A.L.S. 2p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 5.) Concerning the transit of Venus. Refers to Rittenhouse and Mason and Dixon. Cf. Minutes, p.56.
    - Concerning the contents of the first volume of the Transactions, , 1771; 8x6-1/2; American Philosophical Society
      [ca.]. D. 3p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol.1,no.12.) Mostly astronomical observations in this document.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, Feb., 1771; 8x6-1/2; Naso, pseud.
      Buckingham Co.,Va., L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Add.mutilated. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 3.) Sends recipe for making Pompion ale.
    - Letter to Moses Bartram, Philadelphia, March 23, 1771; 10x8; Marshall, Humphry, 1722-1801
      West Bradford, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 9.) Concerning sun-spots and silk worms.
    - Concerning some obvious phenomena of light, June 21, 1771; 12x7-1/2; Colden, Cadwallader, 1688-1776
      [read] D. 3p.and end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 3.)
    - Letter to Isaac Bartram, Nov. 15, 1771; 15x12; Archimedes, S., pseud.
      Conagocheage, L.S. 2p.and end. (see Ms. Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 4.) Concerning a vessel to sail on ice. Cf. Minutes, p.68.
    - Letter to John Ewing, Philadelphia, Nov. 26, 1771; 8x6-1/2; Hutchins, Thomas, 1730-1789
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end.and end. Enc. wanting. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 1, no. 1.) Forwards memoir on the "Country of the Illinois, etc."
    - Delineation of a Solar Shadow, Dec. 6, 1771; 14x4-1/2; Oliver, A. (Andrew), 1731-1799
      D. 1p.drawing. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy. vol.1,no.3.) For fate of paper which accompanied this item, see: APS Minutes, (printed), p.68.
    - Meteorological observations by David Jameson and John Page, 1772; 9x7-1/2; Jameson, David
      Virginia, D. 2p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol.1, no.3a.)
    - Extracts from the minutes, Feb. 1, May 15, 1772; 8x7; American Philosophical Society
      D. 2p.and end. Relative to presentation of the Transactions, B.Franklin is mentioned twice.
    - Letter to Tho[ma]s Coombe, Feb. 2, 1772; 9x7; White, Taylor
      London, A.L.S. 3p.and end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 2.) Sends prints. Natural history. Cf. Minutes, p.72.
    - Astronomical observations, Feb. 7, 1772; 14-1/2x9; Holland, Samuel, 1728-1801
      [read] D.S. 3p. and end. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 10.) Cf. Minutes, p.70. Printed: R.S. Trans., vol. 64, 171.
    - Concerning bathing in Sweden, June 19, 1772; 13x8; Wrangel, Carl Magnus, d. 1786
      [read] D.S. 3p.and end. (see Ms. Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 2.) Cf. Minutes, pp.73,74.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec. 27, 1772; 12-1/4x7-1/2; Howell, Rednap
      Boutetourte County, Va., A.L.S. 3p.and end. Forwards specimen of moss used in dyeing. Plans of a silk reel. Cf. Minutes, p.79.
    - Letter to [David] Rittenhouse, Philadelphia, Feb., 1773; 8x6-1/2; Houston, William Churchill, ca. 1746-1788
      [post]. A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol.1,no.1.) Account of the cold winter.
    - Meteorological observations from Newton township and Philadelphia, June 9, Sept. 30, 1773; 6x4; Pemberton, Israel, 1715-1779
      D. 11p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS Natural philosophy, vol.I, no.5-5b.)
    - Hints for the Philosophical Society, April 2, 1773; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Alison, Francis, 1705-1779
      A.D.S. 3p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no.6.) Printed: Phila.soc.for promoting agriculture. Memoirs,vol.6,127ff. Cf.Minutes, p.79.
    - Concerning the Aurora borealis, April 2, 1773; 8-1/2x7; Thompson, Benjamin
      Bradford, [read] D. 3p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 4.) Cf. Minutes, p.79.
    - Letter to Robert Harris, Philadelphia, Dec. 2, 1773; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Archer, John, 1741-1810
      Balt[imore] County, A.L.S. 2p.and.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 6.) Presents and describes an amphibious animal. Cf. Minutes, p.87.
    - Letter to William Smith, Philadelphia, April 25, 1774; 8x6-1/2; Oliver, A. (Andrew), 1731-1799
      Salem, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Enc.wanting. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1 no. 7.) Forwards paper on water spouts.
    - Meteorological observations near Philadelphia, Jan. 1, Feb. 28, 1775; 13x8; Pemberton, Israel, 1715-1779
      D. 2p.and end. and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 8.)
    - Report of the committee to whom was referred the paper on the extraordinary cold at Northampton during, January, December 22, 1776, 1804; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; American Philosophical Society
      Philadelpia, 1 p. A.D.S.: James Mease. Work published in Transactions of Royal Society of London; therefore precluded from those of A.P.S.
    - Account with the American philosophical society, Jan.12-Jan.31, 1776-1791; 7-1/2x9; Aitken, Robert, 1735-1802
      Philadelphia, D. 3p.and end. Mentions binding two volumes especially for B.Franklin.
    - Letter to University of Aberdeen, 1777; 9x6-3/4; American Philosophical Society
      Philadelphia, Photo of A.L.S.: William Smith and Robert Strettell Jones. 2p. Presentation note on Vol.I, A.P.S. Transactions. Presented by University Library Kings's College, Aberdeen, Scotland, 1968.
    - [Nov. 1780] Thermometrical observations at William & Mary College, Madison, James, 1751-1836
      Therometrical observations originally enclosed in a note from Madison to Rittenshouse.
    - Letter to Timothy Matlack, Philadelphia, Sept. 29, 1781; 8x6-1/2; Syng, Philip, 1703-1789
      Lower Merion, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 3.) Concerning the death of his son, John. See Ms. Communications.
    - List of donations made to the APS, Jan. 3, 1783; 16-3/4x11-1/4; American Philosophical Society
      ca. 1793. In hand of John Vaughan. D. 1p.end.
    - Letter to ----, Nov. 6, 1784; 13x8; Brooks, Ebenezer
      Kentucky, A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 1.) Concerning a discovery of perpetual motion.
    - Remarks on the fattening and curing of beef as could be best practiced in America, 1786; 14-1/2x9-1/2; T.,
      D.S.with initial. 5p.and end. (see Ms. Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 7.)
    - Plan of a fan chair, Aug. 18, 1786; 10x8; Cram, John
      D. 1p.and end. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 10) Cf. Minutes, p.144.
    - Concerning magnetism, Feb.7, 1787; 13x8; Churchman, John, 1753-1805
      A.D.S. 18p.and end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 12.) Cf. Minutes, pp.148-149.
    - Letter to Benjamin Franklin, June 11, 1787; 9x7-1/2; Croker, Temple Henry, 1729 or 30-1790?
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 7p., end. and end. (see Ms. Comm.to APS. Natural Philosophy, vol. 1, no.14. ) Windmills and magnetic needle.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, Aug. 16, 1787; 10x8; Churchman, John, 1753-1805
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no.24.) Asks for copy of the report on his paper. Cf. Minutes, p.153.
    - Letter to [Robert] Patterson, Feb. 7 [18], 1791; 9x8; Williams, Jonathan, 1750-1815
      Friday [read] A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 5.) Concerning W.Barton's observations on longevity in the U.S. Cf. Minutes, p.189.
    - Letter to Rob[er]t Patterson, Feb. 17, 1791; 8x6-1/2; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813
      A.L.S. 3p.and end. Enc. wanting. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 10.) Forwards work by Mühlenberg. Cf. Minutes, p.189.
    - Letter to the President of the A.P.S., Oct. 25, 1791; 13x8; Scrupulous, pseud.
      L. 1p.and add.,end. Enc. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. lla.) Encloses memoir for the premium. For enclosure, see: Scrupulous. Concerning...heat and cold upon springs; [read] Nov. 4, 1791.
    - Letter to [Benjamin Smith?] Barton, Aug. 31, 1792; 12x7-1/2; Cutler, Manasseh, 1742-1823
      Ipswich, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol.I, no.3.) Concerning the age of Indian ruins in the Ohio country. Cf. Minutes, p.209.
    - Letter to John Vaughan, Sept. 21, 1792; 9x7-1/2; Barnes, Joseph
      Philadelphia, L. 1p.,end. Enc. of 14p. and 2 drawings. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 12.) Provides plan and calculations for a mill utilizing Rumsey's invention.
    - Concerning an improved manner of gauging, Nov. 16, 1792; 9x7-1/2; W.
      [read] D.S.with initial. 18p.and 1 drawing and end. in hand of D.Rittenhouse. (see Ms. Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 13.) For the premium. Cf. Minutes, PP.209, 210.
    - Letter to the president of the A.P.S. Philadelphia, Jan. 18, 1793; 9-1/2x7; Collin, Nicholas, 1746-1831
      A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 19.) Concerning the climate of Pennsylvania from the records of the Swedish church. Cf. Minutes, p.212.
    - Letter to R[obert] Patterson, Feb. 15, 1793; 10x8; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796
      A.L.S. 1p.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 30.) Concerning a comet. Printed: APS Trans.o.s.,vol. III, 261.
    - Letter to Ferd[inand] R[u]d[olph] Hasler, Switzerland, Oct. 12, 1794; 6-1/2x5; Lalande, Joseph Jérôme Le Français de, 1732-1807
      A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 2, no. 63.) Concerning triangles.
    - Letter to [Thomas Jefferson], May 29, 1795; 9x7-1/2 15-1/2; Vautravers, Jean-Rodolphe, b. 1723
      London, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ms. Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no..) Friendly letter.
    - Concerning the preservation of peach trees, June 2, 1795; 13x7-1/2; Guest, Henry
      Brunswick, A.D.S. 2p.and add: Robert Patterson, end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 11.) Entered for the premium.
    - Description of a new Portable Orrery., August 21, 1795; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841. 7-17-1795
      See Pro. XXII, pt. 3, 233,
    - List of papers presented for publication since [Philadelphia], October 2, 1795; 8" x 13"; American Philosophical Society
      n. d. 4 pp. D.
    - Plan for extinguishing fires, March 6, 1795 (?); 13x8-1/2; Varlé, Charles
      [read] D. 4p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 3.) Cf. Minutes, p.229.
    - Letter to David Rittenhouse, Feb. 29, 1796; 9x7-1/2; Story, Isaac, 1774-1803
      Marblehead, A.L.S. 4p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 31.) Encloses geometrical formula for extracting the square root. Cf. Minutes, p.238.
    - Letter to the President of the A.P.S., Aug. 20, 1796; 10x8; Hall, John
      Trenton, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the A.P.S. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 13.) Concerning illumination of the streets of Philadelphia. Offered for the prize. Cf. Minutes, p.241.
    - Letter to [John] Vaughan, Philadelphia, Sept. 20, 1796; 9x8; Aveilhi,
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p. In French. Enc. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 16.) Concerning a cotton machine.
    - Letter to W[illiam] Barton, Philadelphia, Oct. 1, 1796; 13x8; Hobrow, William
      New Jersey, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 17.) Suggestions on illumination. Offered for the prize. Cf. Minutes, p.249.
    - Concerning the ascertaining of longitude at sea, Oct. 6, 1796; 10x8; Jourdan, W. Crowley
      A.D.S.with initials. 2p.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 32.) Cf. Minutes, pp.242,243,244.
    - Concerning the improvement of chimneys, Dec. 16, 1796; 9x7; D.B.T.P.S., pseud.
      D.S.with initials. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no.20.) Offered for the premium. Cf. Minutes, p.245.
    - Concerning animal cotton and the insect fly carrier, Jan. 3, 1797; 9-1/2x7; Baudry des Lozières, Louis Narcisse, 1761-1841
      Philadelphia, D.S. 9p. In French. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 13.) ----English translation. 9p. Cf. Minutes, p.254. Printed: APS Trans.o.s.,vol.V,150.
    - Concerning a new lamp to light the streets, Jan. 7, 1797; 10x8; Couldery, William
      London, D. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 21.) Offered for the premium. Cf. Minutes, p.259.
    - Letter to the American philosophical society, Feb. 10, 1797; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
      [read]. Resumé of L. 1p. (see APS Ms. Minutes, 1793-1798, p.133.) Printed in part in the APS Minutes: APS Proceedings, v.22,pt.3,248.
    - Concerning water, dioptics, burns and scalds, salt of lime, heat and cold, and the dead in the grave, March 17, 1797; 12-1/2x8; Vanleer, Branson
      [read] A.D.S. 6p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, nos. 20-20c.) Cf. Minutes, p.254.
    - April 21, 1797, Sociedad Económica de Amigos del País de Valencia. 11-22-1796
      its works. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 255-6,
    - Letter to Tho[ma]s Jefferson, May 24, 1797; 9-1/2x8; Williamson, Hugh, 1735-1819
      Trenton, A.L.S. 2p., end. (see Ms. Comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no.16.) Natural history.
    - Letter to C[harles] W[illson] Peale, May 25, 1797; 15x9-1/2; Hutchinson, S. F.
      Presque Isle, A.L.S. 6p.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 1, no. 9.) Concerning Indian ceremonies and music. Cf. Minutes, pp.263, 264.
    - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, Philadelphia, May 28, 1797; 13x7-1/2; Williamson, Hugh, 1735-1819
      New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. (see Ms. Comm. to APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no.15.) Natural history of North America.
    - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, et al, Nov. 7, 1797; 8x6-1/2; Shultz, Benjamin
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 30p. and end. (see Ms.Comm.to APS. Natural history, Vol.1, no.14.) Botany.
    - by order of Government.", December 1, 1797; Williams, Edward. 8-2-1797
      See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 264,
    - Letter to [Thomas Jefferson], Dec. 4, 1797; 9x7-1/2; Coulter, Thomas
      A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Enc. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 18.) Botany. For enclosure see Coulter: Article on... peach trees [ca.Dec. 1797].
    - Description of a ship pump, Dec. 15, 1797; 16x13; Improvement, pseud.
      [read] D.S. 2p.and end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 23.) Offered for the premium. Cf. Minutes, p.264.
    - Letter to [Thomas] Jefferson, Feb. 1, 1798; 10x8; Varlé, Charles
      Canal de la Susquehanna, A.L.S. 1p. and end. (see Ms.Comm.to APS. Medicine, anatomy, & physiology, no.10.) Concerning yellow fever.
    - [Catalogues of the library,], , 1798; 8" x 13" and 8" x 12 1/2"; American Philosophical Society
      2v. Manuscript Incomplete. Along with these is a printed page containing six entries found in the ms. apparently showing intention to print the catalogue. For an account of these catalogues see Library bulletin 1943,p.76.
    - Meteorological observations taken on a voyage from Detroit to Michilemacanac, Aug. 4-Sept. 3, 1798; 12-1/2x8; Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825
      D. 3p.and end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 93.) Cf. Minutes, p.275. For other observations taken by Wilkinson, see nos. 23-24 of Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1.
    - Letter to Jonathan Williams, March 26, 1798; 12-1/2x8; Peters, Richard, 1743-1828
      A.L.S. 1p. Enc. wanting (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 21.) Returns paper on peach trees. His method of preventing decay.
    - Report of committee on the preservation of peach trees, April 4, 1798; 9x7; American Philosophical Society
      A.D.S.: Jon. Williams. 5p.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 21a.) Refers to the essays by "Lime" and "X" Cf. Minutes, p.269.
    - Letter to Thomas Jefferson, June 11, 1798; 9-1/2x8; Turner, George, 1750-1843
      Philadelphia, A.L.S. 6p. and end. (see Ms.Comm. to APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 22.) Concerning the prairie squirrel.
    - Report of committee on Turner's paper on the prairie squirrel, June 22, 1798; 8x5; American Philosophical Society
      A.D.S. B.S.Barton. 2p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 23.) Cf. Minutes, p.273.
    - Letter to Caspar Wistar, Philadelphia, July 30, 1798; 10x8; May, Francis
      Nashville, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 17.) Concerning fossils.
    - Pro., November 23, 1798; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841. 11-23-1798
      XXII, pt. 3, 273,
    - Thermometrical tables taken at Detroit, Oct. 16, June 17, 1798, 1799; 13x7-1/2; Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825
      D. 7p.and end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 23-24.) Cf. Minutes, p.275. For other observations taken by Wilkinson, see no. 93 of Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2.
    - Catalogue of the American philosopical society library, , 1799; 8x7; American Philosophical Society
      original card misplaced A.D.in hand of Nicholas Collin. 2vols. For report of the catalogue, see: APS. Report...; Dec. 13, 1799. Cf. Minutes, Dec.13, 1799.
    - Act of incorporation, 1799; 9-1/2x8; Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences
      [ca.]. D. Copy by Simeon Baldwin. 4p.,end. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 1, no. 11a) Cf. Minutes, p.290. Enclosed originally in letter from the Conn.Academy to Adam Seybert; Dec. 25, 1799.
    - Letter to Robert Patterson, Feb. 27, 1799; 9x7-1/2; Wynkoop, Henry, 1737-1816